בוקר טוב. Boker tov. All right, today's דף daf is מ"ח, Mem-Chet,
48, and we pick up at the last line, the very last
line of מ"ז עמוד ב, Mem-Zayin Amud Beis, and we just had
a fascinating debate about whether you say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on שמיני עצרת,
Shemini Atzeret, that שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is its own חג, chag,
its own רגל regel in various ways. Even though that was clearly
acknowledged, all the ways it was distinct, the question was, was that
distinct enough for a separate שהחיינו? Shehecheyanu? And the גמרא Gemara ended
by saying, we'll just read, I guess, two lines from the bottom
of מ"ז עמוד ב, Mem-Zayin Amud Beis, והלכתא, V'hilchasa, and the הלכה
halacha is אומרין זמן בשמיני החג, omin zman b'shemini hachag, you do
say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. תני כוותיה דרב נחמן,
Tani k'vasei d'Rav Nachman, and we taught like רב נחמן Rav Nachman
this, which is this הלכה, halacha, that we do say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu
on שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. And here's the ברייתא, Braisa, it's actually
a תוספתא: Tosefta: שמיני רגל בפני עצמו, Shemini regel bifnei atzmo, שמיני
Shemini is considered its own יום טוב, Yom Tov, its own holiday
לעניין פז"ר קש"ב, l'inyan pezer keshev, and here's a nice mnemonic: פז"ר
קש"ב. pezer keshev. What do these six things mean? פ, Pe, ז,
Zayin, ר, Reish, ק, Kuf, ש, Shin, ב, Beis, each one stands
for a way in which שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is distinct. Number
one: פ, Pe, פיס בפני עצמו, pais bifnei atzmo, its own lottery.
What does this mean? They would do a lottery in the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. If you remember, on each group, the כהנים kohanim
were divided into 24 groups. Each group operated on a separate, for
a separate week, so every group would operate two weeks out of
the year,
roughly. But on the רגלים, regalim, all the groups would operate at
the same time. And how would they therefore distribute the various קרבנות
korbanot that they would bring on the רגלים regalim if everybody is
operating at the same time? They would have a lottery. For those
who recently learned with us יומא, Yoma, you remember that they had
a lottery even on a daily basis within the group, when even
it was only one group, to decide who gets to do some
of the early services of the day. But here they would also
have a lottery in terms of distributing the קרבנות korbanot of מוסף
Musaf between the groups. Now, over סוכות, Sukkot, there were a lot
of animals brought for the קרבנות korbanot for סוכות. Sukkot. 13 bullocks,
it started with 13 bulls, 14 sheep, two rams, and so
on. And then the number of bulls would decrease over the days.
So anyway, for the purposes of just thinking about the bulls, okay,
if there were 24 groups, basically the way they would operate is
that everybody would, they'd have one representative of each person, they all
get into a circle, they'd randomly, you know, do some pick a
number, randomly count from a particular person, start with that person. And
then that group would get one of the bulls, and then it
would go, the next one would get the next bull, next next,
and so on and so forth, dividing up the bulls of that
day. Well, over סוכות, Sukkot, there were 70 bulls, right? Everybody knows
פרי החג parei hachag is 70. Divide 70 by 24, and what
do you get? Three with, you're two short of getting three, right,
almost three. So basically the bulls would be distributed, you go all
the way around and they'd be distributed over the סוכות, Sukkot, so
that every group of כהנים kohanim would get three bulls, except two
groups, the last two, would only get two. Fine. Then you came
to שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret there is actually
only one bull, as we discussed yesterday. So you figure you might
as well give that to one of the remaining two groups, right,
to get as much equity as possible. No, פיס בפני עצמו, pais
bifnei atzmo, not because of the separate, it's basically an independent day,
you start, you do a completely new lottery, and somebody else, and
whoever wins that lottery is going to get that bull, that group,
and it has nothing to do with a continuation of the past.
So besides what we've seen, what the גמרא's Gemara going to mention
in a minute, קרבן בפני עצמו, korban bifnei atzmo, that just the
nature of the קרבנות, korbanot, the animals, are not part of the
same series as what preceded, even the question of, well, we might
as well, you know, continue where we left off for a certain
degree of equity, that even that we're not doing. We start with
a brand new פיס. pais. So that's the פ: Pe: פיס בפני
עצמו. pais bifnei atzmo. ז: Zayin: זמן בפני עצמו. zman bifnei atzmo.
That's what we've been discussing: it gets its own שהחיינו, Shehecheyanu, straightforward
enough. ר: Reish: רגל בפני עצמו, regel bifnei atzmo, it's its own
רגל. regel. That's a little bit of a tautology. Here's the six
ways in which it's its own רגל: regel: it's its own רגל.
regel. So what does the ר Reish mean? So רש"י Rashi says
it means that you do not sit in a סוכה, Sukkah, do
not take a לולב. Lulav. That's certainly what the גמרא Gemara emphasized
earlier, that the primary מצוות mitzvos of the חג chag do not
of סוכות Sukkot do not apply by שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. Now,
that's more of a lacking than something relating to its own positive
identity, it's more of a negative identity. We'll talk about that a
little bit later today when we get to a משנה Mishnah in
the middle of the page. But right now, even if it doesn't
tell you anything about the positive identity of שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret,
it certainly tells you that it is not considered part of סוכות.
Sukkot.
Okay, by the way, I should just point out that תוספות Tosafot
says the רגל בפני עצמו regel bifnei atzmo is... different point. It's
that it has the power to stand for a seven-day יום טוב
Yom Tov when it comes to issues of אבילות, Aveilus, right, if
people know about the, you know, the idea that if somebody, if
somebody let's say,
God forbid, a family member dies and it's right before יום טוב,
Yom Tov, let's say right before סוכות. Sukkot. So comes along יום
טוב, Yom Tov, and that stops the שבעה. Shiva. Then there's still
שלשים. Shloshim. Then the days of like חול המועד סוכות Chol HaMoed
Sukkot also count towards like deducting away from the שלשים, Shloshim, and
then also how do you count שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeret? So an
interesting thing is that שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret itself counts as like
a seven-day חג Chag in terms of deducting the days of שלשים.
Shloshim. So there actually is a way in which the whole of
שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret itself counts as its own independent יום טוב
Yom Tov and like even like a seven-day חג Chag for aspects
of אבילות. Aveilus. That's another interpretation תוספות Tosafot gives for the רישא
Reisha of רגל בפני עצמו. Regel Bifnei Atzmo. Okay, but anyway more
simply it's just the idea of that it does not have the
same, the same מצות Mitzvos of סוכות. Sukkot. קורבן בפני עצמו, Korban
Bifnei Atzmo, now we're up to כ"ש"פ, Kaf-Shin-Pei, קורבן בפני עצמו, Korban
Bifnei Atzmo, that's easy. That's its own קורבנות. Korbanos. As we said,
not part of the same series. It's not, you know, part of
the decreasing number of cows, it's one cow. It's not fourteen sheep,
it's seven sheep. It's not two rams, it's one ram. Its own
קורבן. Korban. שירה בפני עצמה, Shira Bifnei Atzma, the כהנים Kohanim would
sing a separate שירה Shira in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. The
songs of סוכות Sukkot that they would sing with the מוסף Musaf
of the קורבנות Korbanos of סוכות Sukkot would be around the, around
the giving of the gifts to the poor from the
agricultural harvest and this would be something different. תוספות Tosafot says that
it possibly is למנצח על השמינית. Lamnatzeach Al HaSheminis. And ברכה בפני
עצמה, Bracha Bifnei Atzma, the ב', Beis, ברכה בפני עצמה. Bracha Bifnei
Atzma. What's ברכה בפני עצמה? Bracha Bifnei Atzma? רש"י Rashi again connecting
it to the earlier גמרא Gemara says it means that in the
liturgy you have a separate name. You don't call it חג הסוכות,
Chag HaSukkot, you call it יום שמיני חג העצרת הזה. Yom Shemini
Chag HaAtzeret Hazeh. Okay, other possibilities also about what this could mean,
but anyway רש"י Rashi says maybe a special blessing that was given
to the king. But more simply the ב' Beis is the special
name in the liturgy. The ר', Reish, רגל בפני עצמו Regel Bifnei
Atzmo is that it does not have the מצות Mitzvos of סוכות
Sukkot
and therefore clearly is, it is its own distinct יום טוב. Yom
Tov. Okay, so now we turn to quite important about all ways
in which שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret has a distinct identity. I'm going
to get back to one of those points in a minute after
the next משנה. Mishna. Not this one, the following משנה. Mishna. Let's
take a look. החליל Hechalil
now that was the ways, and that all was an explanation of
the משנה Mishna that said that לולב וערבה Lulav V'Arava are six
and seven days. And we discussed the taking of the לולב Lulav
on שבת Shabbos and taking of ערבה Arava on שבת Shabbos and
הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabba. Then we have next משנה Mishna that specifically
addressed הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabba. Then we were dealing with the end
of סוכות Sukkot and הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba and are the לולב
ואתרוג Lulav V'Esrog still אסור Asur הוקצו למצותן? Huktzu L'Mitzvasan? And that
got us into the discussion about the status of these objects of
מצוה Mitzva on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret and the status of שמיני
עצרת Shemini Atzeret to begin with. Now we're going back to the
opening משניות Mishnayos though that talks about things that last X number
of days during the, during סוכות Sukkot because there's so many different
מצות Mitzvos and so many days. So we mentioned לולב וערבה Lulav
V'Arava six and seven. Now we get to ההלל והשמחה שמונה. HeHallel
V'HaSimcha Shemona. הלל Hallel you say for all eight days.
סוכות Sukkot in this way is distinct from פסח. Pesach. פסח Pesach
according to the עיקר הדין Ikar HaDin you only say הלל Hallel
on the first day. Our מנהג Minhag of course to say a
half הלל, Hallel,
the גמרא Gemara notes the מנהג, Minhag, but to say a half
הלל Hallel the rest of the days, but the full הלל Hallel
is only said on the first day of פסח Pesach whereas סוכות
Sukkot it's every day. Every day is distinct. גמרא Gemara explains that
that's based on the idea that it's different קורבנות Korbanos each day
so it's considered that every day has its distinct identity. So הלל
Hallel is eight days and שמחה Simcha is eight days. שמחה Simcha
of eight days here does not mean שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis
HaShoeiva, we'll get to that. שמחה Simcha of eight days here means
the שמחה Simcha of bringing the שלמים Shlamim on יום טוב, Yom
Tov, שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha was done for eight days. כיצד? Keitzad?
Now the focuses in on the שמחה Simcha which is interesting. Oh
my gosh, look at that. Thank you. It focuses on the שמחה
Simcha because as I said there's a חידוש Chiddush to the הלל
Hallel aspect as well that סוכות Sukkot is distinct from פסח. Pesach.
But it focuses on, thank you, it focuses on the שמחה, Simcha,
מלמד שחייב אדם בהלל ובשמחה ובכבוד יום טוב אחרון של חג כשאר
כל ימות החג. Melamed shechayav adam behallel uvesimcha uvechavod yom tov acharon
shel chag kish'ar kol yemot hachag. A person is obligated in הלל
Hallel and שמחה Simcha and honoring the last day of יום טוב
Yom Tov like all the other days of יום טוב. Yom Tov.
Again, honoring the last day of יום טוב Yom Tov is, you
know, not such a חידוש, Chiddush, you honor the last day of
יום טוב Yom Tov on פסח Pesach as well. But the חידוש
Chiddush here is the הלל Hallel and the שמחה. Simcha. The הלל,
Hallel, the bigger חידוש Chiddush is that you say it every day.
The real חידוש Chiddush is
is that שמחה, Simcha, the שלמי שמחה Shalmei Simcha which we always
know applied to the entirety of a רגל Regel like by פסח,
Pesach, here it also goes to the very last day as well,
which is part of particularly a חידוש chiddush as we have noted
once we realize that the last day is a distinct day, it
is not part of the holiday of סוכות. Succos. And nevertheless, the
שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha continues through שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. And that's
where we'll see, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
מנא הני מילי, Mina hani milei, where do we know this idea
that the שלמי שמחה shalmei simcha continues through שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres.
דתנו רבנן, Detanu Rabbanan, our Rabbis taught: והיית אך שמח, Vehayisa ach
sameach, you shall be only exceedingly, or you should be as happy.
לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון, Lerabbos leil Yom Tov ha'achron, now that
extra thing, why does it say again be happy? It just said
be happy. It's to tell you even the last day of יום
טוב. Yom Tov. Now what does this mean? You have to look
at it in context. If you look at the פסוק posuk being
quoted in דברים Devarim 16. Okay,
so it says: חג הסוכות תעשה לך שבעת ימים באספך מגורנך ומיקבך.
Chag HaSuccos ta’aseh lecha shivas yamim be’ospecha migornecha umiyikvecha.
Notice what's not mentioned here: שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. Seven days of
סוכות. Succos. ושמחת בחגך אתה ובנך ובתך ועבדך ואמתך והלוי והגר והיתום
והאלמנה אשר בשעריך. Vesamachta bechagecha atah uvnecha uvischa ve’avdecha va’amasecha vehalevi vehager
vehayasom veha’almanah asher bish’arecha. שבעת ימים תחוג לה’ אלקיך במקום אשר יבחר
ה’, Shivas yamim tachog la’Hashem Elokecha bamakom asher yivchar Hashem, כי יברכך
ה’ אלקיך בכל תבואתך ובכל
מעשה ידיך. ki yevarechecha Hashem Elokecha bechol tevu’asecha uvechol ma’aseh yadecha. Again,
no שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. ובכל ובכל מעשה ידיך Uvechol uvechol ma’aseh
yadecha והיית אך שמח. vehayisa ach sameach. שלוש פעמים בשנה יראה כל
זכורך את פני ה’ אלקיך במקום אשר יבחר בחג המצות ובחג השבועות
ובחג הסוכות ולא יראה את פני ה’ ריקם,
Shalosh pe’amim bashanah yera’eh chol zechurecha es penei
Hashem Elokecha bamakom asher yivchar bechag hamatzos uvechag hashavu’os uvechag hasuccos velo
yera’eh es penei Hashem reikam, איש כמתנת ידו כברכת ה’ אלקיך אשר
נתן לך. ish kematnas yado kevirchas Hashem Elokecha asher nasan lach.
All the three רגלים, regalim, no שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. סוכות, Succos,
seven-day holiday. So here's another evidence of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres really
being separate. So the גמרא Gemara says, how do you know שמחה
simcha applies to שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeres? It says ושמחת בחגך Vesamachta
bechagecha after saying it's a seven-day חג. chag. No mention of שמיני
עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. שבעת ימים Shivas yamim
it says. So the answer is והיית אך שמח, Vehayisa ach sameach,
only happy, even more happiness is coming to say even beyond סוכות,
Succos, even the day of שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. Now, the גמרא's
Gemara's language is ליל יום טוב האחרון. leil Yom Tov ha'achron. Why
ליל יום טוב האחרון? leil Yom Tov ha'achron? You don't bring a
קרבן korban at night. This is about שלמי שמחה. shalmei simcha. רש"י
Rashi says, no, that's why also it's addressing how do you say
it includes שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres if the פסוק posuk is talking
about סוכות? Succos? Because you brought the קרבן korban on סוכות. Succos.
You brought it on this day of סוכות Succos on day seven.
But a קרבן korban that you bring, the שלמים shelamim that you
bring, you eat not only the day but you eat the following
night and actually the following day for שלמים. shelamim. Okay? So therefore
אך שמח ach sameach means the שמחה simcha of שלמי שמחה shalmei
simcha of the חג chag is not limited to the day of
סוכות, Succos, but the bringing of it on the חג chag of
סוכות, Succos, but it is the continued eating of it even after
סוכות Succos is over, the continued eating of it that occurs on
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. So let's take a look as the גמרא
Gemara develops this point. One minute, let's see the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so the גמרא, Gemara, so the ברייתא Baraisa says like this: לרבות
ליל יום טוב האחרון. lerabbos leil Yom Tov ha'achron. או אינו אלא,
O eino ela, maybe it's only יום טוב הראשון? Yom Tov harishon?
Maybe it's coming to tell you to include the first night? Because
although you have to have שמחה simcha the first night, but again
if שמחה simcha means שלמי שמחה, shalmei simcha, then you don't bring
a קרבן korban at night. So we would be talking about a
קרבן korban that would be brought ערב סוכות. Erev Succos. So is
there an idea of eating שלמי שמחה, shalmei simcha, is there a
מצוה mitzvah of the שמחה simcha of eating קרבנות korbanos that applies
on the night of the חג chag if the קרבן korban wasn't
brought on the חג chag itself, it was a קרבן korban that
was brought yesterday? How much focus is on the bringing, how much
focus is on the eating? So let's take a look. כשהוא אומר
אך, Keshehu omer ach, when it says only happy, חלק chilek or
חלק, chalak, it's not both, we're not that there's an extra happiness
but let's not go overboard, only some opportunities, not others. Okay? ומה
ראית לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון ולהוציא ליל יום טוב הראשון? Umah
ra'isa lerabbos leil Yom Tov ha'achron ulehotzi leil Yom Tov harishon? Fine,
so you've got to pick one, we're not going to go overboard.
So why did you pick the last day of יום טוב Yom
Tov for שמחה simcha and not the first day? מרבה אני ליל
יום טוב האחרון שיש שמחה לפניו, Marbeh ani leil Yom Tov ha'achron
sheyesh simcha lefanav, I pick the last day which is preceded by
שמחה simcha because the קרבן korban would be brought on סוכות Succos
itself and then the continued eating would be מוצאי סוכות, Motzaei Succos,
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeres. ומוציא אני ליל יום טוב הראשון שאין שמחה
לפניו Umotzi ani leil Yom Tov harishon she'ein simcha lefanav and I'll
exclude the first
night which does not have שמחה simcha that precedes it. Now of
course you could have made the opposite argument, not the first day,
the first night. I'll include the first night which is סוכות Succos
proper, which is eating on סוכות, Succos, and I'll exclude the last
night which is not eating on סוכות. Succos. Clearly it seems to
indicate, you know, I you could read it otherwise, but it seems
to indicate obviously the importance of the bringing of the קרבן, korban,
you know, as a central part of what this is about. Because
it's not just our experience of שמחה. simcha. The גמרא Gemara says,
you know, the famous line people quote: אין שמחה אלא בבשר ויין
Ein simcha ela bevasar veyayin is not in the גמרא. Gemara. The
גמרא Gemara actually says: אין שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים. Ein simcha ela
bevasar shelamim. והשתא דליכא שלמים, Ve'hashta delika shelamim, you know, it says
everybody with what makes them happy. The, I forget, the men with
wine, women with nice clothes, you know, interesting גמרא Gemara about certain
gender assumptions. But okay. But the point is, by the way, it
doesn't even say בשר ויין, basar veyayin, it just says יין, yayin,
although the רמב"ם Rambam has בשר ויין basar veyayin somehow, maybe a
bit different גירסא. girsa. But it emphasizes in the time of the
מקדש, Mikdash, אין שמחה אלא בבשר שלמים. Ein simcha ela bevasar shelamim.
Now again, the question is, it's not like the meat of a
sacrifice tastes better than a meat of a non-sacrifice. It's that the
שמחה simcha that comes through the connecting with God, through that larger
sense of wholeness, of importance, of meaningfulness, that comes by bringing it
in the presence of God. That's the שמחה. simcha. So therefore, how
much of it is the eating or how much is it the
eating as the culmination of the act of having brought the קרבן.
korban. And that's what this גמרא Gemara is saying, that actually there
is no מצוה mitzvah of שמחה simcha on the first night of
יום טוב Yom Tov because it wasn't part of bringing the קרבן
korban on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Only there's only שמחה simcha on
the last night because it extended from the bringing of the קרבן
korban that occurred on סוכות Sukkot itself, and that is central to
the idea of the שמחה. simcha. The שמחה simcha of being in
the presence of God is a central idea to the שמחה simcha
of יום טוב. Yom Tov. In a way, you could also see
this playing out in the בית Beit of nowadays, whether שמחה simcha
is in terms of כולו להשם kulo l'Hashem or
כולו לכם. kulo lachem. How much is the idea of שמחת יום
טוב simchat Yom Tov about our own pleasure and how much is
it about spending all your time learning? But the intersection of the
two, the eating of the קרבן korban brought in the presence of
God is very central to this idea. Now, a few other points
and then we'll let Michael ask this question. Number one, while we're
talking about the aspect of שמחה, simcha, it's worth noting that in
the תורה, Torah, the פסוקים psukim I just read you, the idea
of שמחה simcha on יום טוב, Yom Tov, although we say it
applies to all ימים טובים, yamim tovim, in the תורה Torah really
is underscored by סוכות, Sukkot, not by other areas. Now why is
that? Probably because, think by the way just about the פסוק pasuk
about the taking of the לולב lulav and the אתרוג. etrog. Right
at it says ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon da
da da ושמחתם לפני השם אלקיכם שבעת ימים. u'semachtem lifnei Hashem Elokeichem
shivat yamim. שמחה Simcha is clearly a reality of סוכות. Sukkot. It
is the end of your agricultural cycle. You spent your whole year
praying for rain, having the planting the crops, harvesting, crops are drying
out. Now you're bringing it all into the house, and there's a
tremendous amount of joy of all the things everything you've accomplished over
the year. And therefore, there's just generally tremendous amount of joy during
that period. And the message of the תורה Torah is that joy
should be directed to God, והיית אך שמח. v'hayita ach sameach. But
שמחת בית השואבה, Simchat Beit Hashoeivah, שמחה simcha of taking the לולב
lulav and אתרוג, etrog, that there's a type of a prayer and
using these
agricultural products to express our joy for all of this success to
God. So a key part about this is that the שמחה simcha
that you have at this time of the year has to come
into the context of the חג chag and be addressed to God.
But the רמב"ם Rambam makes another important point because, in a way
it's really the פסוקים, psukim, because the פסוקים psukim I just read
you have another thing that in this context, not just thanking God
and not just sitting in a סוכה, sukkah, but the פסוקים psukim
actually say the following: ושמחת בחגך. v'samachta b'chagecha. Who is משמח? mesameiach?
אתה ובנך ובתך ועבדך ואמתך והלוי והגר והיתום והאלמנה אשר בשעריך. atah
u'vincha u'vitecha v'avdecha va'amatecha v'halevi v'hager v'hayatom v'ha'almanah asher bisharecha.
And these are the people who, as I mentioned before in the
centrality of the מצוה mitzvah of the מתנות לעניים matnot l'aniyim of
the, I'm sorry, I mean פורים Purim מתנות לאביונים, matnot l'evyonim,
anyway about the מתנות עניים matnot aniyim and about the agricultural gifts
to the poor. You're gathering it in and things drop and the
לקט leket and the שכחה shichcha and all of that. These are
the ones that at this time have to make sure that their
needs are attended to. Everybody is so happy with all of their
wealth and success. How about the people that don't have land and
that don't have any of this? And making sure that they are
attended to and the obligations of מתנות לעניים. matnot l'aniyim. So רמב"ם
Rambam points out, connects these two ideas with the מצוה mitzvah of
שמחה. simcha. And I'll just read you very briefly from a very
powerful רמב"ם. Rambam. Hold on, let me just pull it up.
That's what he says about הלכות פורים. Hilchos Purim.
Yeah, so this is a רמב"ם Rambam that he says in general
about the idea of שמחת חג. simchat chag. It's in הלכות יום
טוב. Hilchos Yom Tov. Hold on a second.
שביתת יום טוב, Shevitas Yom Tov, I think that's it, let's see
if I remember where it is.
One
second.
Oh, here
he goes. He says: שמחה אמורה היא קרבן שלמים כמו שאנו מבארים
יש בכלל שמחה לשמוח הוא ובניו וביתו וכל אחד כראוי לו.
Simcha amurah hi korban shelamim kmo she-anu mivarim yesh bichlal simcha lismoach
hu
u-vanav u-veito v'chol echad k'ra'ui lo.
So primary שמחה simcha is שלמים, shelamim, but nowadays as everybody is
appropriate for them. So he mentions what you get for kids, what
you do for the women, אנשים אוכלין בשר ושותין יין. anashim ochlin
basar v'shotin yayin. So it's the רמב"ם Rambam that says בשר ויין
basar v'yayin somehow maybe but different גירסא. girsa. And that's an interesting
issue. Whether you have to have meat on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
you know, like on שבועות, Shavuos, and other people generally prefer not
to have meat. The גמרא Gemara says יין, yayin, the רמב"ם Rambam
says אין שמחה אלא בבשר. ein simcha ela be-basar. Anyway,
here the רמב"ם Rambam says, and then he goes on. He says:
So, you have meat and wine, etc. וכשהוכל ושותה חייב להאכיל לגר
ליתום ולאלמנה ושאר העניים האומללים, U-k'she-hu ochel ve-shote chayav le-hachil la-ger la-yatom
ve-la-almana ve-sha'ar ha-aniyim ha-umlalim, right
when you're eating you have to invite all of the, you know,
poor and the and the orphan and the widow and all of
those that would nor- would that are what? Less fortunate. Those that
are less fortunate, exactly. אבל מי שנועל דלתות חצרו ואוכל ושותה הוא
ובניו ואשתו ואינו מאכיל ומשקה לעניים ולמרי נפש,
Aval mi she-no'el daltot chatzero ve-ochel ve-shote hu u-vanav
ve-ishto ve-eino ma'achil u-mashke la-aniyim u-le-marei nefesh,
you lock your doors, you and your whole family are enjoying all
of your sumptuous food but you do not feed to any of
the poor and the unfortunate. אין זו שמחת מצווה אלא שמחת כרסו.
Ein zo simchat mitzvah ela simchat kerso.
This is not a שמחת מצווה, simchat mitzvah, it's a joy of
your stomach. ועל אלו נאמר זבחיהם כלחם אונים להם כל אוכליו יטמאו
כי לחמם לנפשם. Ve-al elu ne'emar zivcheihem k'lechem onim lahem kol ochlav
yitama'u ki lachmam lenafsham. ושמחה כזו קלון היא להם. Ve-simcha kazu kelon
hi lahem.
This is an embarrassment. שנאמר וזריתי פרש על פניכם פרש חגיכם. She-ne'emar
ve-zeriti peresh al pneichem peresh chagichem. So pretty harsh words from the
רמב"ם Rambam there in הלכות יום טוב Hilchos Yom Tov at the
end of פרק ו. perek vav.
So that is a nice connection since we're talking about שמחת יום
טוב simchas yom tov and the שמחה simcha of שלמים, shelamim, talking,
you know, and just going why is שמחה simcha underscored in the
תורה Torah by סוכות? Succos? Number one, it's a חג chag of
שמחה simcha where that is the general experience and number two, it's
also the under- the emphasis of the of the—what do you call
it?—of the—I'm sorry, hold on, something's happening here on my phone—the emphasis
on the poor and the unfort- and the less fortunate and how
that is part of the שמחה. simcha. Okay, now, the other thing
to mention is this idea of the last night of יום טוב.
Yom Tov. First of all רש"י Rashi says once you're including שמיני
עצרת Shemini Atzeret and the night of שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, then
of course by a קל וחומר kal v'chomer the day would be
included as well and bringing a קרבן korban a שלמי שמחה shalmei
simcha during the day of שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. You would. Right.
It's not so obvious that that's true. You could say that no,
in the end of the day it's still seven days of שמחה,
simcha, it's just that the night of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is
the culmination of the קרבן korban that was brought during the day
of סוכות. Succos. That's not so clear. The other thing that is
not so clear is: Are you obligated to bring a קרבן korban
every single day when you're there? Are we saying that if you
didn't bring on the first day, are we saying there's a קיום
kiyum of שמחה, simcha, there's an idea of שמחה? simcha? I mean
really every day that you're there you have to bring a separate
שלמים? shelamim? Gets pretty expensive to be עולה לרגל. oleh l'regel. So
that is not so clear. I mean the language of this makes
it sound—it's—it's ambiguous, לרבות ליל יום טוב האחרון לשמחה. lerabbos leil yom
tov ha-acharon le-simcha. It doesn't sound like you're חייב, chayav, you know,
it's part of the idea of שמחה simcha includes that last night.
There remains a clear—a definite ambiguity here about what is the idea
of, you know, of שמחה simcha and how much are you obligated
to bring a קרבן korban every single day or at least every
other day since you can eat a קרבן korban for two days,
you know. But that remains somewhat ambiguous here and what therefore including
the last night of יום טוב Yom Tov actually means. Okay, Michael,
were your questions answered? Almost all of them.
No, oh, so tell me more. So this קרבן korban I guess
is not specifically for יום טוב, Yom Tov, but some קרבן korban
you choose to bring. Correct. So you can actually still bring it
on יום טוב. Yom Tov. Correct. That was one thing. The other
is that it still seems to me then that the first night,
you know, we should all make a big deal out of sort
of gets a little bit less.
In terms of this form of שמחה, simcha, that is correct, you
know, then the question becomes how much does our contemporary שמחה—right, simcha
so our contemporary שמחה simcha is a קיום kiyum of שמחה simcha
without this. That is true.
It's very often it's like a גזרה שוה gezeira shava ט"ו ט"ו,
tet vav tet vav, you have to eat a כזית kezayit in
the סוכה, Sukkah, right, same as פסח. Pesach. We're at least still
eating on the first night a כזית kezayit of something in the
סוכה, Sukkah, bread, but it doesn't necessarily mean we're having like a
big meal?
No, no, no. It's just the שמחה simcha of שלמי שמחה. shalmei
simcha. And when we have a different form of שמחה, simcha, then
that would apply the first night. Okay, let's take a look at
the משנה. Mishna. Next משנה. Mishna. סוכה שבעה כיצד? Sukkah shiva keitzad?
What how would you have—what does it mean now right we're going
so these, you know, these things are eight days, סוכה Sukkah seven
days. So what does it mean? I mean it's pretty straightforward, so
let's take a look. גמר מלאכול, Gamar mil-echol, you're done eating
on
הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, you've had your last meal, you've had breakfast
or something, you're not going to eat again till the night, till
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret.
לא יתיר סוכתו, Lo yatir sukkato, don't undo your סוכה Sukkah because
you you might have to eat an- you might want to eat
eat some more before the day is over. אבל מוריד את הכלים
מן המנחה ולמעלה, Aval morid et hakelim min hamincha u-l'mala, from מנחה
mincha time onwards you start taking your stuff out of your סוכה
Sukkah into your house. מפני כבוד יום טוב האחרון של חג, mipnei
kvod yom tov ha-acharon shel chag, to show honor of the last
day. So this sounds like ideally you should be taking apart your
סוכה, Sukkah, but since technically you can't because you need it around,
you do the next best thing. Now why is that important for
the כבוד יום טוב האחרון של חג? kvod yomtov ha-acharon shel chag?
Well, the simple explanation is that you've got your bed up there
and you've got your nice dishes up there and you're going to
need them for שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret in your house, so in
order to get your house ready for שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, you
got to get that stuff down. But the משנה, Mishna, there's a
subtext of something else going on. It sounds like there's an aspect
of... of כבוד יום טוב האחרון של חג Kavod Yom Tov Haacharon
Shel Chag by just leaving your סוכה. Sukkah. Ideally you should be
taking apart your סוכה Sukkah except technically you can't because you might
need it. Let's see how that idea is continued in the גמרא.
Gemara. Okay. אין לו כלים להוריד מהו. Ein lo kelim lehorid mahu.
If you don't have any vessels and vessels here means like bedding
as well to bring into your house, what do you do? So
the גמרא Gemara says, אין לו כלים? Ein lo kelim? You don't
have any vessels? אלא כי אשתמש מאי אשתמש, Ela ki ishtamesh mai
ishtamesh, what have you been using the whole week? What have you
been sleeping on? What have you been eating off of? But notice
by the way, okay, that's a reasonable question, but notice by the
way the funny nature of the assumption of the original statement. You
don't have vessels to bring down, what do you do? It sounds
like again like there's a point of showing that you're leaving your
סוכה, Sukkah, right? Oi, what do you do? Who cares? So you
don't have vessels to bring down, okay, whatever. So maybe I've already
got them in the house or who knows? This idea that you
need to be doing something to bring your vessels down indicates an
assumption that there's an act you have to do to show you're
abandoning the סוכה Sukkah and moving into the house. And this is
continued in the answer. So the גמרא Gemara first wants to understand
what does it mean you don't have vessels, what have you been
using the week? אלא אין לו מקום להוריד כלים מהו. Ela ein
lo makom lehorid kelim mahu. So now it understands no, actually let's
say you don't have any place in your house to bring it
in. You have to be in your סוכה, Sukkah, I don't know,
they're redoing your kitchen or something, you can't go back into your
house. So what are you supposed to do? You can't leave your
סוכה. Sukkah. So again, what's the problem? So okay, so you'll eat
in your סוכה Sukkah which is שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. But let's
see what the answer is. רבי חייא בר רב Rabbi Chiya bar
Rav or בר אשי אמר bar Ashi amar פוחת בארבע. pocheis baarba.
You have to invalidate your סוכה. Sukkah. Make a hole in it
four טפחים, tefachim, that invalidates. תוספות Tosfos asks why four, why not
three, whatever. Invalidate your סוכה. Sukkah. רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi omer מדליק בה נר, madlik bah ner, light a
candle in your סוכה. Sukkah. And we learned before that a small
סוכה Sukkah you light a candle in it, you're not supposed to
light a candle in it. Everybody's going to be anxious about the
fire hazard. ולא פליגי Velo pligi and they don't disagree. These are
two different solutions for two different scenarios. הא לן והא להו. Ha
lan veha lehu. That's for them, this is for us. Meaning for
those in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and those in בבל. Bavel. Why
is there a difference? Because as we just learned, those in בבל
Bavel what do you have to do on שמיני עצרת? Shemini Atzeret?
You have to eat in the סוכה. Sukkah. So if you're in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael you don't have to eat in the סוכה
Sukkah on שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret so you can invalidate it. Make
a big hole in it. But if you're in בבל, Bavel, if
you're out of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, you need to eat in
a סוכה, Sukkah, you can't make a big hole in it. But
what do you do? You gotta do something to show it's not
really סוכות. Sukkos. So you bring in and you light a candle
which normally is very unadvised and it does not allow you to
feel so comfortable in your סוכה Sukkah because you're always anxious that
a fire is going to break out. And that you do even
though you can't invalidate it, even though you have to eat in
it, you still need to do something to undermine the significance of
eating in the סוכה. Sukkah. Fascinating idea. Until now all we've talked
about is not making a ברכה, bracha, although we did say somebody
who said an opinion that said don't eat in the סוכה. Sukkah.
But now not making a ברכה bracha is not enough, you have
to actually show it's not really סוכות Sukkos that you don't really
belong there. Let's keep on reading. הא לן והא להו. Ha lan
veha lehu. התינח סוכה קטנה. Hateniach Sukkah ketanah.
That's good for a small סוכה Sukkah where a candle is disruptive.
אלא בסוכה גדולה מאי איכא למימר? Ela beSukkah gedolah mai ika lemeimar?
A big סוכה Sukkah where you're not afraid that the candle is
a fire hazard, you put it in the middle of a table,
there's a lot of space around it, what can you do that
would be comparable? מעייל בה מאני דמיכלא. Meiayeil bei mane demichla. You
bring dirty dishes into it. You leave all your dirty smelly dishes
in your סוכה. Sukkah. ואמר רבא Veamar Rava because in general you
would never do that for a סוכה. Sukkah. Because רבא Rava has
taught מאני דמיכלא בר ממטללתא, mane demichla bar mimetaltasa, your dirty dishes
you bring out of your סוכה. Sukkah. מאני דמשתיא במטללתא, mane deshtaya
bimetaltasa,
your drinking glasses you can leave in a סוכה, Sukkah, right? When
you're clearing the table you want to get rid of the dishes
right away. The glasses you don't have to get rid of right
away, it's not so disgusting, it's not so bad. So this is
a type of a thing you would normally never do during סוכות,
Sukkos, leave your dirty dishes there. Here you leave your dirty dishes
even if you're eating on שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, you have to
eat without a ברכה, bracha, you have to show it isn't really
סוכות, Sukkos, you really don't belong here. Now it's pretty funny. I
don't know anybody, even those that have the מנהג minhag to eat
like myself, מנהג minhag you know, follows גמרא, Gemara, excuse me, to
say that you should eat in a סוכה Sukkah on שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeret and make a point of making it like uncomfortable, you
know. So I don't know, we don't exactly do this. But that
being said, what the point I want to bring out, important about
שמיני עצרת, Shemini Atzeret, because to me this is like, I
have a very strong שיטה shitta about what this גמרא Gemara indicates
about שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. Because the assumption here is that it's
important for שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret not just that you have your
bedding and your dishes in the house, it's important that you leave
your סוכה, Sukkah, right? How do you show you're leaving your סוכה,
Sukkah, says the גמרא, Gemara, if you don't have what to take
down? How if even if you have to be in a סוכה
Sukkah you're making it clear you've left your סוכה? Sukkah? And the
idea that part it's important to leave your סוכה Sukkah for כבוד
יום טוב האחרון. Kavod Yom Tov Haacharon. And to me I think
that this is a way of understanding what שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret
is all about. Like everybody asks what's the יום טוב yom tov
about? All the stuff about being רגל בפני עצמו, regel bifnei atzmo,
all the ways it's not סוכות, Sukkos, it's all very lovely. It's
not סוכות, Sukkos, so what is it? What is its identity? What
is it supposed to be? So there's a very interesting תרגום אונקלוס.
Targum Onkelos. אונקלוס Onkelos says on the פסוק pasuk ביום השמיני עצרת
תהיה לכם, Bayom hashemini atzeret tihyeh lachem, what does עצרת atzeret mean?
Gathering in.
אונקלוס Onkelos says on And ביומא תמינאה אצרתא מן מטלליא לביתייא. bayoma
timinaia atzarta min mitalalaya leveitaya. It should be a gathering in from
your סוכה sukkah into your house. But he understands that the idea
of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is the leaving of the סוכה sukkah
and going into the house. It's the transition back into the home.
Because if you think about it, as we all know, the hardest
things in life are the follow-through, right? So you go to a
conference and you have all these wonderful ideas you're going to bring
back to work, and then as soon as the plane lands back
where you're from, you've forgotten all of them and you're back to
the day-to-day, right? And so the whole idea is you've spent the
entire ימים נוראים Yamim Noraim talking about bringing God into your
life, right? And ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, going
into the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. Then we took the experience of
the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim and we took it out of just
the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, and סוכות Sukkot was we brought it
into the סוכה. sukkah. Because so much as we discussed סוכות Sukkot
is the idea of, you know, of being in the presence of
God, of the ענני כבוד. Ananei HaKavod. The גמרא Gemara evokes the
symbolism of the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kodashim, of the כרובים, Keruvim, of
the מילואים, Miluim, of being, God is right there, we've taken God,
we've brought God into our house, into the סוכה. sukkah. That is
the move, we're trying to do the follow-through from יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. But the thing is, it's a lot easier to have that
type of a consciousness while you're there in the סוכה. sukkah. The
real challenge is now going back into your real house, like getting
really back into the day-to-day and into the normal rhythms. How do
you take God, and how do you take that sense of the
presence of God back with you in the rest of the year?
And so that's my understanding about what the idea of שמיני עצרת
Shemini Atzeret is, focusing on that transition, what it means to be
moving back into the house. So that's why I think, you know,
the גמרא Gemara about רגל בפני עצמו regel bifnei atzmo and this
גמרא Gemara of כבוד יום טוב אחרון, kevod Yom Tov acharon, that
yes, part of the idea of שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeret is demonstrating
that you're leaving your סוכה sukkah and doing it with a consciousness
of what it means to be leaving your סוכה sukkah to be
going into the house and to be beginning the rest of the
year. So we need a יום טוב Yom Tov that makes us
stop and pause before we start the rest of the year while
we're in our house. Now we're back in our houses, how we're
going to take everything that's preceded this whole last month and make
sure that that now stays with us. So that's my ווארט vort
on this גמרא, Gemara, and I think a very important understanding of
שמיני עצרת. Shemini Atzeret. Couple questions, Michael?
That's very interesting. I was thinking though that doesn't it really seem
to fit in with the last... oh who cares. No but you
know what I mean though is that if
you're still in the סוכה, sukkah, it's sort of like a negative
act, right? But isn't that sort of a focal point when you're
enjoying the actual יום טוב? Yom Tov? I'm sitting here having my
nice meal, I'm looking at a bunch of dirty, smelly dishes, you
know what I mean?
Yeah, you know, I assume it means in a somewhat of a
symbolic way. You gotta figure out how to strike the right balance,
which is probably why we don't do it today, yes.
It's a little light on the תפילה tefillah for leaving the סוכה
sukkah
though, right?
But what does the תפילה tefillah say? יהי רצון שיזכה. Yehi ratzon
sheyizkeh. Yeah,
the תפילה tefillah doesn't really talk about the transition into the house,
it just says we look forward to the messianic times when we'll
all dwell in a סוכה, sukkah, right? Have to figure out if
I can tie that תפילה tefillah into my ווארט, vort, into my
explanation, I don't know.
I think this is the first time the studies are לשון בהוצאה,
lashon behotza'ah, usually it's לשון בהכנסה. lashon behachnasah.
Well, the assumption is, I think we have had it once before,
I think it is because as רש"י Rashi points out, the assumption
that the סוכה sukkah is on the roof, so you're bringing it
down into your house, yes.
And also we have all that discussion of שהחיינו Shehecheyanu and now
the language of כלים. keilim. So we say שהחיינו Shehecheyanu when כלים
keilim is like a piece of clothing.
Does the חכמים Chachamim have like a broader... if I bought a
new
pot, can I say שהחיינו?
Shehecheyanu? Well again, you know, the פסק psak is it depends how
much of a שמחה simcha it is. There's not a clear categorization
of that. Alright, let's take a look now at the next משנה.
Mishnah. ניסוך המים כיצד? Nisuch hamayim keitzad? Pouring of the water is
the is for seven days, okay. So now we're going to discuss
the pouring of the water that they did with the morning sacrifice
on סוכות. Sukkot. How was that done? צלוחית של זהב מחזקת שלושה
לוגים. Tzelochit shel zahav mahazeket shlosha lugin. So a golden
vessel, pitcher, that contained three לוג log of water. A לוג log
is here's the best way that I remember how much these things
are. A רביעית revi'it is our minimum size of like a kiddush
cup, it's about three and a half ounces. A רביעית revi'it is
a quarter of a לוג. log. So a לוג log is about
fourteen ounces. So three לוג log is thirty, forty-two ounces, which is
like what, which is a little bit more than half of one
of those two-liter bottles of soda, right? Those are like seventy-something ounces?
Whatever. Anyway, so that's three לוג. log. Okay. So they would fill
it up, היה ממלא מן השילוח, hayah memaleh min haShiloach, from the
שילוח Shiloach which was a wellspring outside of the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. הגיעו לשער המים, Higiu leSha'ar HaMayim, they came to the gate
of water which was on the south side of the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash near the ramp towards of the altar. תקעו והריעו ותקעו.
Tekau veheriu utekau. They did תקיעה, תרועה, תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah, We
saw that before that they did that by the ערבה. aravah. So
all these rituals in the מקדש, Mikdash, particularly these ones in the...
At the side of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, reached שער המים
*Shaar HaMayim*, came to the gate of the water which was on
the south side of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* near the ramp
towards of the מזבח mizbei'ach, *Mizbeach*. תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah,
*Tekiah Teruah Tekiah*, they did תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah, *Tekiah
Teruah Tekiah*. We saw that before that they did that by the
ערבה *Aravah*. So all these rituals in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*, particularly
these ones that are all around water and so much about סוכות
*Sukkos* is about prayer for water. Anyway, so they did a תקיעה
tekiah, תרועה teruah, תקיעה tekiah. *Tekiah Teruah Tekiah* with these rituals. עלו
בכבש *Alu b'kevesh*, the הכהן *Kohen* went up the ramp ופנה לשמאלו
*ufano l'smolo*, he turned left. שני ספלים של כסף היו שם *shnei
sfalim shel kesef hayu sham*. Normally you turn right, we'll discuss that
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. And there were two funnels of silver.
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, אומר *Rabbi Yehudah omer* של סיד היו *shel
sid hayu*, they were actually made out of plaster אלא שהיו מושחרים
פניהם מפני היין *ella she-hayu mushcharim pneihem mipnei hayayin*, but they looked
black and they looked silver because of the wine that was poured
down them. ומנוקבים כמין שני חוטמים דקים *u'menukavim k'min shnei chotamim dakim*,
and they had holes in them like two thin nostrils. אחד מעובה
ואחד דק *echad moveh v'echad dak*, one was thicker and one thinner,
which רש״י *Rashi* says to mean one was a larger hole
and the other was a thinner hole. כדי שיהיו שניהם כלים בבת
אחת *kedei she-yiyu shneihem kalim b'vas achas* because you're going to pour
both the wine and the water. Wine you brought every single day
with קרבנות *korbanot*. Water was brought only seven days of the year,
only on סוכות *Sukkos*. Okay? And the water was brought with the
morning תמיד Tamid, *tamid*. So, and you would pour the wine and
the water that you're bringing with the morning תמיד Tamid. *tamid* at
the same time into the two different funnels. One of the funnels
was only used seven times a year. Of these two funnels, one
of them was for water. So you poured the two and they
wanted the wine and the water to flow through the funnels and
to finish at the same time. So therefore you had them different
thicknesses, or the openings were different sizes because wine is more viscous
than water. So therefore you want a wider opening for the wine
because it's the same quantity of liquid so that if you want
the wine and the water to go down at the same rate.
כדי שיהיו שניהם כלים בבת אחת *kedei she-yiyu shneihem kalim b'vas achas*.
מערבו של מים מזרחו של יין *maaravo shel mayim mizracho shel yayin*.
The west one was water, the east one was wine. I'll just
draw a quick picture here.
Right, here's your north, here's east,
south and west.
I'll actually draw it from over here. Okay, whatever. Okay. So, here
is the altar. Here's your
ramp.
Okay, now the opening was in the south, so somewhere it was
opening here which is the שער המים *Shaar HaMayim*. So they came
in through here, went up the ramp, okay, and now he went
left because he's going to do it on this corner. All right,
so normally you turn right, but that's going the long way around.
He went the short way around and there were two funnels at
the corner. Let's look now so that we have our altar. Okay,
fine.
Anyway,
so here he is. Okay, he's at this corner and there are
two funnels.
There's one on the east and one more western. Okay, so he's
at this corner and
he's pouring the wine into the funnels. All right, so it says
אחת של *achat shel* where were we? Okay. אחת מערבו של מים
*achat maaravo shel mayim*,
the one on the west,
closer to the אולם *Ulam*
right, was of,
was the one for the wine. Where was he? No. מערבו של
מים *maaravo shel mayim*, that's right, was one for the water. מזרחו
של יין *mizracho shel yayin*, the one on the east, wine. Now,
עירה של מים לתוך של יין ושל יין לתוך של מים *ira
shel mayim l'toch shel yayin v'shel yayin l'toch shel mayim*, if accidentally
he poured the water into the wine one or the wine into
the water one, יצא yotze, *yatzah*, still fine. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
אומר *Rabbi Yehudah omer*, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda, *Rabbi Yehudah* said, ולא
היה מנסך כל שמונה *v'lo hayah menasech kol shmonah*. Two ways he
disagrees. It was not three לוג log, *log* of water, it was
only one לוג log. *log*, and it was not seven days, it
was all eight days including שמיני עצרת *Shmini Atzeret*. ולמנסך אומר לו
*u'lamenasech omer lo*, and to the guy who was pouring the water
they said to him, הגבה ידך *hagbeh yadcha*, lift up your hand,
let's see you pour the water and let's see you pour it
into the funnel. שפעם אחת *she-pa'am achat*, one time, נסך אחד על
גבי רגליו *nasach echad al gabei raglav*, he refused to pour in
the funnel, he poured on his feet. Now
he was not trying to demonstrate it because apparently he was doing
it in a hidden way because he didn't want to get in
trouble, which is why now they say "let's see what you're doing."
But the reason he did it was because he was a צדוקי
*Tzadoki*, and the צדוקים *Tzadokim* did not believe in this ritual of
ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim *nisuch hamayim*, and he did not want to
go along with it. So he poured on his feet. But people
saw it ורגמוהו כל העם באתרוגיהם *u'regamuhu kol ha'am b'etrogayhem*, and everybody
stoned him with their אתרוגים *etrogim* because everybody's in the בית המקדש
*Beis HaMikdash* with their אתרוגים *etrogim* and לולבים *lulavim* as we learned
earlier.
Exactly. So now they wanted to see him do it publicly to
make sure that he would be pressured by the crowd and do
it in the right way. Okay. כמעשהו בחול כך מעשהו בשבת *k'ma'asehu
bachol kach ma'asehu b'Shabbos*. He would do on the weekday like he
did on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*, the pouring of the water. אלא שהיה
ממלא מערב שבת חבית של זהב שאינה מקודשת she'einah mekudeshet *ella she-hayah
memale m'erev Shabbos chavit shel zahav she-einah mekudeshet*. But you can't draw
the water from outside of the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* and bring
it in
to you'd be carrying. So ערב שבת *Erev Shabbos* you would fill
it in a barrel that was not sanctified. The reason you would
do it not sanctified is if... the water became sanctified by being
in the barrel, it would become invalid by spending over the night,
פסול בלינה. pasul belinah So therefore you do not want to sanctify
the water yet because you have to take care of this Friday
afternoon. Okay? שאינה מקודשת מן השילוח. min haShiloach. Okay, ומניחה בלשכה u-manichah
balishkah
and they would keep it in the לשכה lishkah in the מקדש
and then on the actual day of שבת they would take from
that barrel. נשפכה, nishpachah, if that barrel spilled, or נתגלתה, nitgaltah, or
it was uncovered, and the גמרא Gemara has a problem with גילוי
gilui uncovered water because it was, it's concerned that it becomes poisonous
and snakes drink from it and so on. We'll discuss that. היה
ממלא, hayah memalei, so if you can't use this water, היה ממלא
מן הכיור, hayah memalei min hakiyor, you would fill it from the
כיור kiyor which is the, you know, the laver, the place where
the כהנים Kohanim would wash their hands, שהיה היין והמים מגולים פסולים
לגבי מזבח shehayah hayayin vehamayim megulim pesulim legabei mizbei'ach because uncovered water
and wine would be invalid, so they would get it from the
כיור kiyor like you'd have the whole
like like a laver
here where they would wash their hands. And it would be there,
the downside is it would not be flowing water. You know, the
idea of as we're going to see, it's going to quote the
פסוק pasuk which is ושאבתם מים בששון ממעייני הישועה. ush'avtem mayim besasson
mima'ainei hayeshuah. And of course the sort of symbolism of flowing and
water, obviously there's a prayer for water, but you know certainly nowadays
and I imagine always, the idea of the metaphor of water as
like the flowing of divine, you know, effluence and קדושה kedushah and
so on, שפע. shefa. So obviously you want flowing water. If you
went from the כיור, kiyor, it was connected to an underground well,
so but that's what you would do if you'd have to fill
it, but that was only a backup. Ideally they would have drawn
the water from the day before from the שילוח. Shiloach.
Okay, it's מים הקדושים mayim hakedoshim from the כיור. kiyor.
It is, but because it's in the underground well, it does not
get its, it doesn't get sanctified, it does not get פסול בלינה
pasul belinah. because it reconnects. You lower it down, the water sort
of is reconnected to the water underneath the ground. So that's certain,
yes, but that is why that's important, but that water does not
become פסול בלינה.
This used to be taking place every day,
every day with the תמיד, with the morning תמיד. Okay, now by
the way, there's an interesting debate
of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot which we'll get to yesterday of
what happens after it goes through this funnel. So רש"י Rashi says
it goes through the
funnel and then it goes onto the מזבח, mizbei'ach. right? Here's the
fire. Okay? And then it gets, goes down into some drain which
brings it into the cavity of the מזבח. mizbei'ach. תוספות Tosafot says
I don't know where רש"י Rashi gets any of this idea, there's
no source for it. Anyway, it'd be pretty, you know, funny for
it to go where all the fire is. תוספות Tosafot thinks it
just goes straight down into some cavity. It never, it never actually
goes on the top of the מזבח. mizbei'ach It's interesting to think
about because we talk about libations of wine, you know, you have
these fires, but where would they be poured? Where on what, where
would it go? So would it actually go on the top of
the מזבח or was it poured at the corner and just went
straight down into...
So רש"י Rashi thinks it goes from the ספל sefel to the
fire and then then a hole?
No, the ספל, sefel, the ספל, sefel, it goes into this ספל
sefel and comes out here and then there's like, I don't know,
you know, it's like some grate or something and then it sort
of goes down after that.
This was ניסוך היין nisuch hayayin for every קרבן korban during the
year and only now we are adding water as a new issue,
as a new element.
Correct. Yep. מנא הני מילי? mena hanei milei? Where do you get
this from? רש"י Rashi says where do you get the idea that
you do תקיעה tekiah? תרועה תקיעה, that you have שמחה simchah that
accompanies it? We're not yet at the basic idea, where do you
get ניסוך המים nisuch hamayim, from? Before we learned it out, we
said it was הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah le-Moshe mi-Sinai. But we'll see
more about where do you get ניסוך המים, Nissuch Hamayim that's not
the exact question right now. רש"י Rashi says the question is how
do you know you do the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, where's the idea
of שמחה simchah come?
תוספות Tosafot says how do you know you draw from a, from
a wellspring from and not, you know, not maybe from just a
well? How do you know from a flowing water? דאמר קרא, de'amar
kra, אמר רב עינא, amar Rav Eina, דאמר קרא, de'amar kra, the
verse says ושאבתם מים בששון ממעייני הישועה. ush'avtem mayim besasson mima'ainei hayeshuah.
So רש"י Rashi says the דרשה drashah is on בששון, besasson, with
joy, and therefore you do the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, and תוספות Tosafot
says it's ממעייני הישועה mima'ainei hayeshuah and therefore you do it from
a stream.
Who says that בששון besasson is תקיעה?
I don't know. All right, fine, I don't know. הנהו תרי מיני,
hanei tarei minei, now there were these two heretics. Anytime the גמרא
Gemara, says heretics, it very often, if not always, refers to Jewish
Christians. So there's actually a good book called, from many years ago,
called "Jesus and Christianity in the Talmud" by this guy Herford Travis,
I think. Anyway, he is Travis, actually a, what, Herford Travis, Herford,
I can't pronounce his name, Travers, I say. Anyway, he is Travers,
actually a, what, Herford Travers. He was a priest or a minister,
I forget which one. Anyway, but he did a very good job
collecting all the references in the בבלי Bavli and the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
even stuff that had been censored out on Jesus and Christianity, and
he just gives like historical context for it. know, and what type
of allusions and what the references were and so on. This particular
גמרא, Gemara I do not know how to translate in, you know,
in terms of some Christian context. But let's take a look. Okay,
so there were these two מינים, minim, these two heretics. חד שמיה
ששון, Chad shmeih Sasson, one's name was Sasson, וחד שמיה שמחה, v'chad
shmeih Simcha, and one's name was Simcha. אמר ליה ששון לשמחה, Amar
leih Sasson l'Simcha, so Sasson said to Simcha, אנא עדיפא מינך, ana
adifa minach, I'm greater than you, דכתיב, d'chtiv, ששון ושמחה ישיגו, Sasson
v'simcha yasigu, they will achieve Sasson and Simcha, so Sasson got mentioned
first. אמר ליה שמחה לששון, Amar leih Simcha l'Sasson, Simcha said back
to Sasson, no, אנא עדיפא מינך, ana adifa minach, I'm better than
you, דכתיב, d'chtiv, שמחה וששון ליהודים, Simcha v'sasson layehudim, Simcha and Sasson
came to the Jews.
אמר ליה ששון לשמחה, Amar leih Sasson l'Simcha, Sasson said to Simcha,
חד יומא שבקוך ושוויוך פרוונקא. Chad yoma shavkuich v'shavyuich parvanka. One day
they're going to abandon you, kick you out of your status in
heaven, and make you some like runner, you know, that goes in
front of the king. דכתיב, d'chtiv, כי
בשמחה תצאו, Ki b'simcha tetzeu, because with Simcha they will go out,
you'll be like the guy who runs in front of the troops
or whatever, or runs in front of the king's retinue. אמר ליה
שמחה לששון, Amar leih Simcha l'Sasson, so Simcha said back to Sasson,
חד יומא שבקוך ומלו בך מיא. Chad yoma shavkuich u'malo bach maya.
One day you'll be abandoned and they'll turn you into some type
of a flask and they'll fill you, fill you with water. דכתיב,
d'chtiv, ושאבתם מים בששון. Ushavtem mayim b'sasson. You will draw water with
Sasson. Like Burp? Oh, that's good timing. So אמר ליה ההוא מינא
דשמיה ששון לרבי אבהו, Amar leih hahu mina d'shmeih Sasson l'Rabbi Abbahu,
so a particular מין min whose name was Sasson, presumably the same
guy, I don't know, said to רבי אבהו, Rabbi Abbahu, עתידיתו דתמלו
לי מיא לעלמא דאתי. Atiditu d'timlu li maya l'alma d'atei. In the
world to come, you will be my water drawers. You Jews, let's
say, will draw water for me. דכתיב, d'chtiv,
because the verse says, ושאבתם מים בששון. Ushavtem mayim b'sasson. You will
draw water, he read it, for Sasson, for me. אמר ליה, Amar
leih, he said back, אי הוי כתיב לששון, Ei hava ktiv l'Sasson,
if it were written for Sasson, כדקאמרת, k'd'ka'amart, then it would be
like you said. השתא דכתיב בששון, Hashta d'chtiv b'sasson, now that it
says with Sasson, משכא דההוא גברא משוינן ליה גודא ומלינא ביה מיא,
Mashka d'hahu gavra mashvinan leih guda u'malina beih maya, the skin of
that man, your skin,
we'll make into a flask and we'll use that to fill water.
So that's what it means, you know. So רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
often had these discussions with the מינים. minim. Again, very little funny
interlude. I have no idea what it has to do with seeing
a מין min other than being a troublemaker, but the first story
was just being silly, so you know, it's a way of poking
fun at the מין. min.
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu in קיסריה, Kesaryah, yeah, he lives
in a pagan city.
Interesting. Interesting. Is it trying to, is the גמרא Gemara trying to
say this is how מינים minim do, they come up with these
ridiculous scriptural...
yeah, I mean a general undermining of the whole enterprise of their
attempt to understand scripture and use scripture. That could be. Because obviously
Jewish scripture's whole idea was to find support,
you know, in scripture
for their religion and for their philosophy. So you could be right.
It could be just a general mocking of that, their whole enterprise.
They don't understand פסוקים, psukim, they don't know how to read פסוקים,
psukim, they're just foolish. What?
Especially in regards to ושאבתם מים, ushavtem mayim, which is not in
the פסוקים.
psukim. Right. Right.
That's interesting too. Right. Okay. עלה בכבש ופנה לשמאלו. Ala b'kevesh u'fana
l'smalo. Went up the ramp and turned left as opposed to the
normal turning right. Went straight to the corner you needed. תנו רבנן,
Tanu rabanan, כל העולים למזבח עולין דרך ימין. Kol ha'olim l'mizbeach olin
derech yamin. Anybody who goes up the altar, you go up on
the right side of the ramp, ומקיפין ויורדין דרך שמאל, u'makifin v'yordin
derech smol, and you come down on the left side of the
ramp. So it's not England, all traffic's on the right. חוץ מן
העולה לשלושה דברים הללו, Chutz min ha'ola l'shlosha dvarim halalu, except for
going up for three things, שעולה דרך שמאל וחוזר על העקב. she'oleh
derech smol v'chozer al ha'akev.
You go up on the left, you make an immediate left turn,
and then you turn around and come back down. ואלו הן, V'eilu
hen, and these three: ניסוך המים וניסוך היין, nisuch hamayim v'nisuch hayayin,
the pouring of the wine and the water. Talk about Christianity, wine
and water. ועולת העוף כשרבתה במזרח, v'olat ha'of k'sheravta bamizrach,
and if there's too much bird עולות olos in the east.
Normally, the bird עולה olah would be here, and the bird חטאת
chatas would be here. But a bird עולה olah was very frequently
brought. It was a way to bring a cheap קרבן, korban, right?
I mean a bird costs very little. So if there were too
many עולות olos here, you'd have to bring the overflow here. So
for bird עולה, olah, then for the pouring, rather than going all
the way around, you made an immediate left. Now רש"י Rashi says
it's not just we want to save you the effort, you know,
it's still more we want the traffic, we always want people moving
to the right, we want to keep the flow of traffic the
same, there's a religious idea of turning to the right, not turning
to the left. But we let you go straight to that corner
because יש כל כך הרבה עשן, yesh kol kach harbeh ashan, there's
so much smoke in that area that the bird will die because
a bird, you know, it's not a big cow, and the bird
will die from smoke inhalation, and the wine and the water will
get smoky and will not be appropriate to be used. So that's
why we let you make an immediate left.
Everywhere, that's what I heard?
Yeah. Anytime you had to bring a bird עולה olah here. The
reason we say a bird עולה olah is that the bird חטאת
chatas was done on the floor. The עולה olah was done at
the top. So anytime you need to bring a bird עולה olah
or anytime you need to do a ניסוך. nisuch. You could make
an immediate left. Okay, so let's keep on going. אלו שהיו משחירים.
Elu shehayu mashchirim.
So the statement was, they were not silver, the funnels, they were
according to the position of whoever it was, רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda,
they were plaster, but they were black because they looked silver because
of the wine. So the גמרא Gemara says, בשלמא דיין משחר, Bishlama
deyayin mashcher, I get that the one used for wine was black
because it was used for wine. אלא דמיא אמאי משחר, Ella demaya
amai mashcher, the one for water, why was it black? It was
used for water! אפי' דאמר מר עירה של מים לתוך של יין
ושל יין לתוך של מים יצא, Afilu de'amar mar irah shel mayim
letoch shel yayin veshel yayin letoch shel mayim yatza, since we say
בדיעבד bidi'avad if you did it the wrong way you're יצא, yotze?
so של מים אתי לאשחורי, shel mayim ati le'ashchurei,
so the water one will sometimes you'll make a mistake and you'll
pour wine down it and it'll so therefore it came, it became
black as well even though it was not used exactly. Now it's
quite fascinating because you could all you have to say is sometimes
the person made the mistake. Why do you have to make the
legal point and saying since בדיעבד bidi'avad you would be יצא? yotze,
Either
you're you never were supposed to do the wine in the water.
Why not just say sometimes people made a mistake? Very important what
it shows you psychologically. Once you tell somebody בדיעבד bidi'avad you're יצא,
yotze. they're not going to be as careful.
So it's a greater likelihood you'll make a mistake now that you
were told that בדיעבד bidi'avad it's not so bad, בדיעבד bidi'avad you'd
be יצא. I don't know why it was bad for it to
be black? I don't know. Okay, so it's during the interim of
that time. ומנוקבים כמין ב' חוטמים, Umenukavim kemin bet chotamim, and there
were two holes like two nostrils down the you know respectively the
two different funnels. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא מתניתין רבי יהודה
היא, Leima matnitin Rebbi Yehuda hi, let's say our משנה Mishnah is
רבי יהודה ולא רבנן, velo rabanan, and not the rabbis, meaning the
fact that you needed a wider funnel for the wine. Why? תנן
רבי יהודה אומר בלוג היה מנסך כל שמונה, Tnan Rebbi Yehuda omer
belog haya menasech kol shmona, that you would not use three לוג,
log but you'd only use one לוג. log So the גמרא Gemara
says, that's why you would need different of water. He said you'd
only use one לוג log of water. That's why the wine had
to be wider because you had three לוג log of wine but
only one לוג log of water.
So therefore in order to get them to go down at the
same rate, you need a much wider funnel for the wine.
ואי רבנן, Ve'i rabanan, if it's the rabbis, כי הדדי נינהו, ki
hadadi ninhu, there's three לוג of wine and there's three לוג of
water. So who needs different size holes? They should go down at
the same rate. So there's an obvious answer. גמרא says, no, אפילו
תימא רבנן, Afilu teima rabanan, even the rabbis would need different size
holes.
חמרא סמיך מיא קליש, Chamra samich maya kalish, wine is viscous, water
is not viscous, and therefore even the same quantity you need a
wider funnel for the wine if you want it to go down
at the same rate. הכי נמי מסתברא, Hachi nami mistabra, that also
makes sense.
Where am I? דאי רבי יהודה רחב וקצר אית ליה, De'i Rebbi
Yehuda rachav vekatzar it lei, because if it's רבי יהודה, רחב וקצר,
rachav vekatzar, he uses the phrase to describe the different funnels, not
the phrase that's in the משנה Mishnah of דק ומעובה, dak ume'uve,
thin and thick, but wide and narrow. דתניא, Detanya, we learn in
a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר שני כסוות היו שם, Rebbi Yehuda
omer shnei kasvot hayu sham, he uses a different phrase, he refers
to these funnels as כסוות, kasvot, two כסוות kasvot were there, אחד
של מים ואחד של יין, echad shel mayim ve'echad shel yayin, one
of wine, one of water. So של יין פיה רחב, shel yayin
piha rachav, the wine one had a wide opening, של מים פיה
קצר, shel mayim piha katzar, and the water one a narrow opening.
So he uses the phrase רחב וקצר, rachav vekatzar, whereas our משנה
Mishnah used the phrase מעובה ודק. me'uve vedak. So כדי שיהו שניהם
כלין בבת אחת, kedei sheyehu shneiem kalin bevas achat, and they were
different openings so that they would run it would run out at
the same time. So שמע מינה, shema mina, that is a good
proof that clearly our משנה Mishnah is not רבי יהודה, it uses
different terminology, but even if it's the רבנן rabanan and even the
same quantity you need different size holes in order so that because
they're different viscosity, so that is enough of a reason to have
different size holes in order that it should all pour out at
the same time. Okay, with that we will end. More of ניסוך
המים tomorrow.